<Document>

# Punishment System

1.	Monetary/Material fines

2.	Community service

3.	Ban on conducting activity (For craftsmen)

4.	Exile from city territory

5.	Hard labor

6.	Retribution through duel

7.	Sent to the arena (If available)

8.	Public execution

# Punishment Modifiers
## Mitigating modifiers:

1.	Self-defense – If the crime was committed to protect one's own life, property, or other people from threat, the punishment may be mitigated or completely cancelled.

2.	Necessity – If the action was committed for survival (e.g., stealing food when starving), the punishment is mitigated.

3.	Inexperience (newcomer) – If the criminal has not previously committed offenses or does not understand the rules (e.g., new player), the punishment may be replaced with training or a warning.

4.	Repentance – If the criminal sincerely repents and is willing to cooperate, the punishment may be mitigated or replaced with compensation to the injured party.

## Aggravating modifiers:
1.	Recidivism – Repeated commission of a similar or more serious crime. Toughens punishment, up to reinforced exile or harsh conditions.

2.	Cultural aspect – If the crime violates religious canons, traditions, or laws of a specific race/faction, this is taken into account (e.g., desecration of a shrine).

3.	Accomplice / Conspiracy – If the crime was committed by a group of persons.

4.	Intention to continue violations – If the criminal, by words or actions, confirms that after release they will continue to commit violations (Works only upon re-arrest).

5.	Victims – If the crime led to serious injuries, death, or destruction of important objects, the punishment is toughened.

6.	Organizer – The one who planned and directed the crime. The punishment will be the strictest (Works only for group violations).

7.	Direct attack – If the criminal acted openly and threatened others, this affects the toughening of punishment.

8.	Wartime – If the crime was committed during a crisis or war, the punishment is toughened (e.g., for sabotage).

</Document>
